<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Big O Theory Club</title>
    <description>Thoughts on theoretical computer science and research life.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 21:45:17 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 21:45:17 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Happy Ending Problem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, Sherry gave a lecture/problem session on the Happy Ending Problem, a popular field of mathematics created by P. Erdös, G. Szekeres, and E. Klein. This problem is very interesting for its connections to Ramsey theory. Her main reference is this &lt;a href=&quot;http://neeldhara.com/ramblings/notes/cgt-01&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 23:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/happy-ending</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/happy-ending</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yet another faculty talk, this week we had and introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo methods by Dr. Eric Vigoda! MCMC methods are super useful in approximating the size #P to count sets, the volume of hard to calculate integrals, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 23:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/monte-carlo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/monte-carlo</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spectral Algorithms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had another faculty talk this week, about how graphs, linear algebra, and algorithms come together in Spectral Algorithms by Dr. Richard Peng. Here is the full abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of large scale data sets in machine learning, statistics, and scientific computing is making increasing use of high performance algorithmic primitives. Tools such as linear systems solvers and convex optimization solvers are integrated in programming languages such as MATLAB, Python, and Julia, and taught as programming constructs in classes. On the other hand, the ever-increasing scale of data, as well as growth in data sources, creates a multitude of new challenges for these primitives: the running times of many, if not most, implementations of linear system solvers and convex optimization tools scale super-linearly with input sizes.
Over the past three decades, works related to efficient solvers for a class of graph structured matrices, graph Laplacians, led to fundamental results in combinatorial optimization and scientific computing as well as the Laplacian paradigm for graph algorithms. In this talk I will survey these progresses, with focus on the underlying algorithm design approaches. Specifically, I will discuss the origin of algorithms that combine combinatorial and numerical building blocks via spectral graph theory, and describe recent efforts on designing new tools tailored towards the overall algorithmic questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 23:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/spectral-algorithms</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/spectral-algorithms</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spooky Problem Session</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Halloween! We had an adeptly themed problem session led by Arvind this week! You can find the problems &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1hmR_X0NY--Zuu3L6LPkOXNbxNwck9BKCCVIPBvDCHE8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/spooky-problem-session</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/spooky-problem-session</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Multi-Armed Bandit Problem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had our first faculty talk by Dr. Jacob Abernethy today! Dr. Abernethy recently joined GT as part of the theoretical CS department. He currently teaches CS 4540 (Advanced Algorithms) and Graduate ML Theory. His talk was on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-armed_bandit&quot;&gt;multi-armed bandit problem&lt;/a&gt; and more generally, solving zero-sum games without the iid requirements that are prevalent in much of ML theory today. Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cc.gatech.edu/news/600231/top-machine-learning-researcher-jake-abernethy-joins-school-computer-science&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about Dr. Abernethy (and his juggling skills).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in an REU, there is a Google doc &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1gG_0dAAmoaLN1rHJsxfR0EGiiWCum6KZ0sBFW2Gy578/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; with helpful information for applying.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/bandit-problem</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/bandit-problem</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Silly Talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone who presented for silly talks today! For the proof that the moon is fake, click &lt;a href=&quot;/files/moon-is-fake.pptx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/silly-talks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/silly-talks</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Provable Security and Cryptocurrency</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had our first student talk this week by Abrahim Ladha on Provable Security and Cryptocurrency. Slides are &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=1sskdo1RqcR7LLX9yx5O9SesEFvPyH-fb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; along with his references below. If you would like to know more about Abrahim, he has a website &lt;a href=&quot;https://ladha.me/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Introduction to Modern Cryptography. Bellare, Rogaway. http://web.cs.ucdavis.edu/~rogaway/classes/227/spring05/book/main.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Vuvuzela: Scalable Private Messaging Resistant to Traffic Analysis. Jelle van den Hooff, David Lazar, Matei Zaharia, and Nickolai Zeldovich. https://people.csail.mit.edu/nickolai/papers/vandenhooff-vuvuzela.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Anonymity and Digital Currency. MIT 6.033 Spring 2018 Lecture 24. http://web.mit.edu/6.033/www/lec/s24.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Provable Security for Cryptocurrencies. Andrew Miller (Thesis). https://www.cs.umd.edu/~jkatz/THESES/amiller-thesis.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] Ouroboros: A Provably Secure Proof-of-Stake Blockchain Protocol. Aggelos Kiayias, Alexander Russell, Bernardo David, Roman Oliynykov. https://eprint.iacr.org/2016/889.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/security-cryptocurrency</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/security-cryptocurrency</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Information Theoretic Message Authentication</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Our student talks coordinator Daniel gave our first student talk of the semester on message authentication in the information theoretic setting. Slides are &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=1EXHtcE6gS4qiJ-RxcrpTjujOfz1fvTKCTBVkvp-7L84&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you are interested in giving a student talk at any point in the semester, please contact one of the officers. We welcome all talks even slightly related to theoretical computer science!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/message-auth</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/message-auth</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Number Theory Problem Session</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This meeting, we had a problem session on various number theory topics, led by Shyamal. The problems were (very) loosely related to the career fair, and were based on this CodeChef lecture &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/_noJI8UkTq8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/number-theory-problem-session</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/number-theory-problem-session</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Computer Vision Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had our second meeting on Tuesday this week because of Labor Day, and instead of a talk, we had a workshop in preparation for the Home Depot Deep Learning Hackathon. Arvind gave an introduction to the field of computer vision along with a simple Keras demo on the MNIST dataset. Slides for the workshop are &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Xyk0Nq-6QzS-pu4l8NNTBZYhcLJFGDxtPsmHRXklyg4/edit#slide=id.p&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://bit.ly/2Cgzn6b&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency, GT’s Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning club, ran a follow-up workshop on Generative Adversarial Networks, an advanced network architecture used in many state-of-the-art computer vision models today. The slides for that are &lt;a href=&quot;http://gtagency.github.io/2018/intro-to-gans&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information about the Deep Learning Hackathon, which is jointly run by us and the Agency can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1006843382831023/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/cv-workshop</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/cv-workshop</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
